#大家好 隔壁大嬸家的那個黃豆哇 現在熟了哦
Hi everyone! The "huang dou" (edamame, lit: yellow beans) grown by our neighbouring auntie are now ready.
#跟她說了一下 叫她搞一點來吃
I've asked her to give us a bit.
#她爽快的答應啦
She agreed without any hesitation.
#因為我們都是鄰居 經常都互相幫忙的
Cuz we're neighbours, we always help each other.
#我家沒種黃豆
I do not grow any "huang dou",
#她家種了好多
and she has a lot.
#去搞一點來吃
I'll get some for us.
#你看 這些黃豆快熟了
Look! The beans here are almost ready.
#你看這
Look at this.
#還帶了把刀過來
I have a knife with me.
#這個葉子不要哦 這個葉子
We don't need the leaves, the leaves.
#先把這個葉子掰掉
So let me remove leaves first.
#掰掉的話就很漂亮了
It will become very pretty after removing the leaves.
#全是豆子
There will be all beans.
#等下我們吃的時候有 我們有整顆[SIC] (註︰他們經常把「棵」誤寫成「顆」，我想我要提一提清哥了)
When we are eating, we can have the whole bunch,
#整顆[SIC]放到在那個鍋裡面去煮
we can boil the whole bunch in a pot.
#看
Look!
#全是豆子 哦
It's all beans, oh!
#毛豆
"mou dou" (lit: hairy beans)
#我叫這邊叫黃豆
It's called "huang dou" here.
#好多毛哦 這個
It's rather hairy.
#不敢 不敢
I dare not, dare not
#不敢鼻子對上去聞
smell it close to the nose,
#毛會戳人的
as the hair stings.
#多砍幾個
Let's get more,
#來都來啦 砍了那麼一點點
as we are already here. Here's just a bit.
#這個豆子
The beans,
#這個根還太小
their roots are too small.
#長得不夠飽滿
They're not really that big.
#我記得以前
I remember,
#我奶奶種的那個黃豆 (註︰我之前全部用"beans"算了，這期不屬教學視頻，可觀性比準確性重要)
that the beans grown by my grandma,
#長好多的 比這個還多得多
were much larger, with much more beans.
#看
Look!
#很靚吧
Isn't it beautiful?
#一串一串的
Strings of,
#黃豆
beans
#夠啦夠啦 我把這個葉子摘啦
Enough, enough. I'll remove the leaves.
#等一下吹多一點 叫隔壁的大嬸一起來吃 (註︰他根本沒有再砍多一點，但不理了)
I'll get more and ask the neighbouring auntie to enjoy with us.
#她也很喜歡吃這個的
She likes the beans a lot too.
#那裡還有個香蕉哦
There're bananas too.
#是我家土裡面長出來的
They're grown from my fields.
#以前還小的時候肯定是我種下去的
It must be planted by myself when I was still a kid.
#搞了那麼一點點
Just got a bit here.
#回去啦
Let's go.
#我都不好意思了
I don't wanna seem too greedy.
#那麼多
There's so much here.
#也不算多啊 這樣
It's not really that much, in fact.
#就那麼一點點
It's just a bit.
#我一個人都可以吃的[SIC]完 (註︰另一個常犯的就是把「的」和「很」混淆)
I can finish it alone.
#哎呀
Aya!
#誰家的 誰家的蘿蔔
Whose, whose radish is it?
#搞幾個過來 (註︰這與以下四句是同一句來的)
Let me get some,
#搞幾個晚上
some, for dinner,
#晚上
dinner,
#晚上炒
dinner, to fry
#炒肉吃
fry with meat.
#這個夢蔔
This radish,
#雖然有點小
is small,
#但是好吃
but it tastes really good.
#這種小蘿蔔
This kind of mini radish
#你看 這是很嫩的哦 這夢蔔 (註︰感覺英文沒有很接近中文的「嫩」的字，所以我想蘿蔔的嫩就是多汁吧)
Look! The radish tastes very tender
#很甜的
and sweet.
#像農村裡面 (註︰不明白，怎麼像農村裡面，不就是在農村了嗎？)
It's just like those,
#種的 這個就是用那個竹鼠
grown in villages. They are fertilized by the waste,
#竹鼠屎燒成的那個灰呀
the ashes obtained by burning the waste from the bamboo rats.
#搞出 種出來的這個 (註︰中英詞序差別關係，這句好像不能譯得太好，隨便放進一些沒意思的算了)
So, is the radish.
#就那麼小一點點
Just a small bunch here.
#把它帶回去
I'll bring it back.
#把這個
I need to,
#這個搞短一點
cut it short,
#不要太大啦
otherwise it's too long,
#那鍋放下大 (註︰之後隱約聽到「鍋太小」，但原字幕沒有，不加了)
too long for the pot.
#你看 這樣我們再把水
Look! I'll then fill it,
#把水放滿一點
fill it with water.
#直接燉它就好了 (註︰他說「燉」但其不是燉，只是開水煮)
Then it can be boiled right away.
#把水放滿
Fill it with water.
#加點鹽下去哦
Put some salt.
#盡量稍微放多一點 (註︰似乎字幕出錯，我聽到的是「鹽要稍微放多一點」)
We need a bit more salt,
#才有鹽味
to ensure the taste of salt.
#畢竟那麼大個鍋
It's a huge pot after all.
#等下它
The beans will,
#嘭起來的話 這樣就熟 (註︰「嘭起來」之前，他說了些話，原字幕沒有，我亦聽不到)
will expand when they're cooked.
#蓋都不見了
The lid is gone.
#你看
Look!
#給我弟
My younger brother,
#被我弟把那個鍋蓋都不知道搞 搞哪裡去了
my younger brother must have placed, placed the lid somewhere else.
#你看這條狗 (註︰他說「這條」，但後來又說「他們」，所以我用了Plural)
Look at the dogs.
#都趴在這裡睡的
They're all having a nap lying on the floor.
#地板上很涼快的哦
The floor must be cool.
#它們還知道讓了一條路出來
They even know leaving a pathway for us.
#我們來把水倒了
Let's pour the water away.
#這有點重
It's a bit heavy.
#小狗讓開讓開讓開
Puppies watch out! Watch out! Watch out!
#等上褪你的毛哦
You wanna get scalded?
#剛好這個開水的哦
I can help with you the boiling water.
#你看
Look!
#這個毛豆 (註︰不想太多音譯，會打擾觀賞雅興，全部用beans算了)
The beans,
#這個黃豆
the beans,
#就 (註︰其實這句沒有說完，他被燙了)
are now
#哎呦
Ayoo!
#那麼燙
so hot!
#我們先吃完這個
Let's finish these first,
#這個等一下再吃
and have the rest later.
#哇 這豆子熟啦
Wa! The beans are alright now.
#嗯
Um!
#很不錯喔
Really not bad!
#剛才不夠鹽
We didn't put enough salt.
#現在加了點鹽
Now I have added some more salt.
#更 更好味啦
It tastes much, much better.
#你看 這個剛摘回來的 新鮮的哦
Look! The beans are freshly picked.
#現在就把它煮熟啦
And now they're cooked.
#砍下來不到半個小時
It's not even half an hour after picking them,
#就下了鍋
when we put them into the pot.
#你看 這豆子
Look! The beans
#掉了一個
I dropped one.
#剛才好叫了一下隔壁大嬸 叫她過來一起吃
I've just asked the neighbouring auntie, asked her to come to enjoy with us.
#她竟然不來
But she's not coming.
#等下我帶點回去給她吃
I'll bring her some later.
#今天的視頻就到這裡啦
The video ends here.